Finding Aid for Vice President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) Records, 1909-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Supplemental Files
  - 1957-2004
    - Facilities and Operations, 1957-1997
      - Wines Field Recreation, 1968-1969 (Box 190)
    - Hospital
      - Miscellaneous, 1998-2001 (Box 191)
      - Arch, 1989-1999 (Box 191)
      - Benefits, 2001 (Box 191)
      - Brighton Health Center, 1982-1998 (Box 191)
      - Budget and Reports to Regents on Financial Operations, 1992-2001; 5 folders (Box 191)
      - Burn Center, 1985-1987 (Box 191)
      - Cancer and Geriatrics Center, 1971-1998; 4 folders (Box 191)
      - Capital Planning, 1992-2001 (Box 192)
      - Chelsea Medical Center, 1992-1994 (Box 192)
      - Clinical Information System, 2001 (Box 192)
      - Communication Disorder Center, 1986-1987 (Box 192)
      - Consultants, 2000-2001; 3 folders (Box 192)
      - Dermatology Satellite Clinic, 1980-1989 (Box 192)
      - Executive Board, 2002; 5 folders (Box 192)
      - Financial Statements, 2000-2001 (Box 192)
      - Helicopter Emergency Services, 1982-2001 (Box 193)
      - Holden Perinatal Research Laboratory, 1969-1986 (Box 193)
      - Investments, 1986-2001; 2 folders (Box 193)
      - Joint Ventures, 1989-1999; 4 folders (Box 193)
      - Lithotripter, 1986 (Box 193)
      - M-Care Health Maintenance Organization
        - 1992-1995, 4 folders (Box 193)
        - Board of Directors, 2000-2002; 8 folders (Box 194)
      - Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), 1981-2000 (Box 194)
      - Maternal and Child Health Care Center -- Mott, 1980-2000; 2 folders (Box 194)
      - Medical Center
        - Parking, 1986-1993; 2 folders (Box 194)
        - Reorganization, 1994-1996; 5 folders (Box 195)
      - Miscellaneous Projects, 1968-1998 (Box 195)
      - Office and Parking Structure, 1974-2001 (Box 195)
      - Organ Transplantation, 1984-1988 (Box 195)
      - Organization, 1992-2001; 2 folders (Box 195)
      - Outpatient Building Addition, 1970-1973 (Box 195)
      - Parkview (Ambulatory Care), 1965-1974 (Box 195)
      - Personnel, 1992-2002 (Box 195)
      - Radiation Therapy, 1977-1994; 2 folders (Box 195)
      - Ronald McDonald House, 1983-1991; 2 folders (Box 196)
      - Sinai Hospital, 1996; 2 folders (Box 196)
      - Substance Abuse Center (Proposed), 1986-1995 (Box 196)
      - Waste Disposal, 1998-2001 (Box 196)
    - Michigan, State of: Investment Advisory Committee
      - 1993-1996, 12 folders (Box 197)
      - 1990-1993, 10 folders (Box 198)
    - Miscellaneous Committees, Groups and Meetings
      - Blue Ribbon Panel on Facilities, 1996; 2 folders (Box 199)
      - Business and Finance Seminar, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 199)
      - Campaign Operations Group, 1992-1996; 2 folders (Box 199)
      - Executive Committee Michigan Historical Collections, 1989-1997; 2 folders (Box 199)
      - Fab 5, 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 199)
        (Robert Kasdin, N. G. Herbert, R. W. Moenart, G. F Schlecht and P. A. Spradlin)
      - Health Alliance, South Central Michigan, 1993-2000 (Box 199)
      - Plant Extension Committee
        - 1996-1997, 3 folders (Box 199)
        - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 200)
      - Sallie Mae Education Services Council, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 200)
      - Six-Pack, 1993-1995; 5 folders (Box 200)
      - Visitors Meetings, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 200)
      - Wayne State University External Review, Financial Operations and Administration, 1996; 3 folders (Box 200)
    - Senate Assembly Committee on Financial Affairs (SACFA)
      - 1997-2001, 12 folders (Box 201)
      - 1990-1999, 14 folders (Box 202)
      - 1977-1989, 4 folders (Box 203)
  - 1979-2004, 2000-2003
    The 2008 accession includes groups of files related to architectural projects on campus (primarily by the Venturi Architecture firm), files from 1994-2004 related to the Unviersity-wide committees on which the CFO served, and files related to the hospital and hospital finances from 1998-2003.
    - Architects
      - Architects -- Miscellaneous, 1979-1998 (Box 216)
      - Venturi
        - Stadium Expansion, 1997-2001 (Box 216)
        - Palmer Drive Site Project, 1999-2001
        - Palmer House, 1997-1999 (Box 216)
        - Parking & Transportation, 2000 (Box 216)
        - Miscellaneous, 1998-2004 (Box 216)
        - Arthur Miller Theater, 1998-2002 (Box 216)
        - Campus Master Plan, 1998-2002 (Box 216)
        - Campus Master Plan, Cont'd, 1997-1998 (Box 216)
        - Campus Master Plan -- Phase II, 1998-2001 (Box 217)
        - CMP Advisory Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 217)
        - Frost House, 1998-2001 (Box 217)
        - Invoices, 1998-2001 (Box 217)
        - Laboratory Design, 1986-1999 (Box 217)
        - Law School, 1998-1999 (Box 217)
        - Life Sciences Institute, 1999-2002; 2 folders (Box 217)
        - LSA Buildings, 1999 (Box 217)
        - North Campus, 1998-2001 (Box 217)
        - Palmer Drive Site, 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 217)
        - UM Heath Systems, 1998-2001 (Box 218)
    - Committees
      - ACLS Investment Task Force, 1998 (Box 218)
      - Ann Arbor Area CEO Council, 1997-2003 (Box 218)
      - Ann Arbor/University Relations, 1998 (Box 218)
      - Audits Advisory Committee, 1999-2003 (Box 218)
      - CIESIN Finance Standing Committee, 1994-1998; 2 folders (Box 218)
      - Committees -- Miscellaneous, 1995-2004 (Box 219)
      - Diversity Committee, 2001-2003 (Box 219)
      - Fiscal Integrity, 2004 (Box 219)
      - Gift Policy Committee, 2000 (Box 219)
      - HR Advisory Group, 2003 (Box 219)
      - IDT Strategic Directions, 1998-2001 (Box 219)
      - NCAA Steering Committee, 2003 (Box 219)
      - NCAA Steering Committee, 2003, 2 folders (Box 219)
      - Peoplesoft Strategic Advisory Council, 1996-1999 (Box 220)
      - Listening Post Meetings, 2001-2004 (Box 220)
      - Listening Post Meetings, 1999-2000 (Box 220)
      - Listening Post Meetings, 1995-1998 (Box 220)
      - Michigan Economic Development Corporation (Life Sciences), 2001-2002 (Box 220)
      - NCAA Fiscal Integrity, 2003-2004 (Box 221)
      - SACFA, 2002 (Box 221)
      - SACFA, 2003; 2 folders (Box 221)
      - Sponsored Program -- Admin. Integration Enhancement Task Team, 2002; 2 folders (Box 221)
      - Technology Transfer Advisory Committee, 2000-2002 (Box 221)
      - Training and Tracking Activities Committee, 2001 (Box 221)
      - Washtenaw United Way -- Independent Oversight Committee, 1996 (Box 221)
    - Hospital (Box 222)
      - Accounts Payable, Accounts Received, Audit, Etc., 2002-2003 (Box 222)
      - Budget, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 222)
      - Capital Planning, 2000-2002 (Box 222)
      - Corporate Compliance, 1998-2002 (Box 222)
      - Gain Sharing, 2001 (Box 222)
      - Healthplex, 2003 (Box 222)
      - Miscellaneous, 2003 (Box 222)
- University Budgets, Accounts and Reports
  The series University Budgets, Accounts and Reports, consists of three subseries: Annual University Budget (official copy); Miscellaneous Unit Budgets (mainly University Hospital); and Project (Trust Fund) Budget.
  The University of Michigan has historically created not one but two university budgets. The document generally referred to as "the budget" and which records most expected university expenses is, in fact, the plan under which general fund money is allocated. The primary sources of general fund income are state taxes and appropriations, as well as tuition and other fees. The "other" budget has been known as either the "Trust Fund" or "Project" Budget. It reports the appropriations of restricted funds. Originally the most common source of restricted funds was various bequests made to the university by individuals to support specific activities or services, such as student loans or research. Thus the accounts were collectively referred to as "Trust Fund Budgets." After World War II the increasing flow of restricted funds from other sources, such as federal funding for construction and research, made the old title obsolete, and the accounts were renamed "Project Budgets."
  Preparation of an Annual University Budget (official copy), appears to have begun in 1909/1910 (an earlier typed budget from 1908/1909 has been listed with this series for convenience). Bound in an oversize format, this document detailed for each unit all employees, each employee's salary history over the previous five years, the requested salary for each employee, and a non-itemized figure for each of the other expenses found in the unit's budget, such as equipment or travel. Each unit's budget was signed by an authorizing official, usually the department chair or dean of the school. Space was allowed so that the authorizing official could, if desired, include a justification for budgetary increase requests. Originally, many authorizing officials did include justification for increased expenses, particularly for higher salaries, but as time passed explanations became rarer. In the last official copy of the university budget, prepared in 1946/1947, explanation had virtually disappeared.
  The physical awkwardness of the official copy of the budget and the need for multiple copies undoubtedly led university officials in 1919/1920 to print copies of most of the budget. Between 1919/1920 and 1947/1948 this bound record was divided into two parts. Part I, "Summary of the Budget," gave a quick overview of university general fund spending. Part II, "Salary Budget," detailed the largest item in the general fund budget. The Salary Budget omitted, however, all non-salary expenses and the optional explanation of changes.
  In 1948/1949 the printed budget was modified. The "Salary Budget" was retitled "Detailed Budget" and its scope was broadened. Non-salary items previously excluded, such as "Current Expense and Equipment" and "Travel" were reported, as well as a few general fund accounts which earlier had not been detailed. A growing concern over the privacy of individual salary figures, led to a major revision in the budget's format in 1956/1957. The Summary/Budget, for convenience long published as a separate document, became the only published document. In place of the Detailed Budget a new publication, called Department Payroll and Accounts, appeared. This document, which had only a limited distribution, included the salary information formerly printed in section II. This salary information also appears in the pages of the Michigan Daily which, relying upon legislation enacted in October 1979, defining state employees' salaries as public records, has annually published the salaries of faculty and professional and administrative employees of the university.
  In 1957/1958, although the Summary Budget continued to be published, a more complete publication, Proposed Budget and Supplementary Schedules was begun. It included the information found in the general fund budget, as well as information about project budgets. This new publication, referred to informally as "the grey book" because of its cover, became the basic budgetary reference tool. In 1965/1966 the volume's title was changed to Budget and Supplementary Schedules. In 1967/1968 it became known by the simple title, Budgets. In 1973/74 the grey book was divided into four volumes, one subtitled "All Campus," the other three giving the budget for each of the university's three major centers, Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint.
  Compared with the complexity of the publications reflecting the university's annual general fund budget, the subseries Trust Fund Budgets, is simple. It began in 1948/1949 with an oversize volume whose format resembled the official copy of the university budget. In 1950/1951 the Trust Fund Budget's format was reorganized to resemble that of the second section of the printed annual budget, the "Salary Budget." As time passed the number of project budgets became large, leading to the binding of multi-volume sets. In 1962/1963 a two volume set was produced. By 1967/1968 twelve volumes were needed to hold all of the budgets. After that year, however, the bulk was reduced and in 1973/1974 the practice of actually binding the budgets together was abandoned.
  In addition to this basic publication of Trust Fund/Project Budgets, the vice president's office also prepared, under various titles, Selected Project Budgets. The reason for these publications was that the budgets of major university units, such as the Institute for Social Research, were difficult to find among the many project budgets. The selected project budget publications made these major units' budgets more accessible.
  Auxiliary Activities, contained the records of units which were substantially self-supporting. A few departmental payroll and account volumes exist for these units, but most of the subseries is made up of annual budgets from the residence halls and University Hospital. The budgets of these two units were probably retained because they are the university's largest auxiliary activities. The hospital, for example, usually accounts for twenty to twenty-five percent of the university's total income and expenses. They are similar in form to the printed annual budget's Detailed Section. The hospital budget contains primarily salary information and also a few general financial tables. It seems to have been modeled on the older official copy of the university budget.
  Reports are the traditional annual accounting which is expected of a major financial institution. Originally prepared for the Regents' scrutiny, today the reports are the basic documents through which the university makes itself accountable for the receipt and expenditure of funds. Two types are generated: Financial (originally Treasurer's) and Investment. The Financial Report, and its predecessor Treasurer's Report, has been issued annually since 1883. It is published in two parts. The first offers a cursory overview of all university income and expenses regardless of the source. The second presents tables detailing income and expenses at the unit level. Because the Financial Report includes both general fund and project income and details both summary salary and non-salary expenses, it is the single most comprehensive document available regarding university finances.
  The Investment Report is a highly specialized document which annually details where the university has placed the funds available to it. Begun in 1928 the Investment Report historically listed the portfolio holdings of each university account. In the mid-1960s the basic structure of the document was changed. Individual accounts were no longer listed. Instead, the university's investment portfolio was reported on as a whole, although the practice of citing each investment instrument by name was retained. The new format made it clear how university funds as a whole were invested, but made it impossible to determine where the funds of a particular account were placed.
  The published annual budget; departmental payrolls and accounts; project budgets; auxiliary activities; reports; and state budget documents are described and located within the Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer publications record group. A separate finding aid has been prepared for these documents.
  - Annual University Budget (official copy)
    - 1908/1909 (Box 25)
      (typescript)
    - 1909/1910-1913/1914 (Volume 1)
    - 1914/1915-1917/1918 (Volume 2)
    - 1918/1919-1921/1922 (Volume 3)
    - 1922/1923 (Volume 4)
    - 1923/1924 (Volume 5)
    - 1924/1925 (Volume 6)
    - 1925/1926 (Volume 7)
    - 1926/1927 (Volume 8)
    - 1927/1928 (Volume 9)
    - 1928/1929 (Volume 10)
    - 1929/1930 (Volume 11)
    - 1930/1931 (Volume 12)
    - 1931/1932 (Volume 13)
    - 1932/1933 (Volume 14)
    - 1933/1934 (Volume 15)
    - 1934/1935 (Volume 16)
    - 1935/1936 (Volume 17)
    - 1936/1937 (Volume 18)
    - 1937/1938 (Volume 19)
    - 1938/1939 (Volume 20)
    - 1939/1940 (Volume 21)
    - 1940/1941 (Volume 22)
    - 1941/42 (Volume 23)
    - 1942/1943 (Volume 24)
    - 1943/1944 (Volume 25)
    - 1944/1945 (Volume 26)
    - 1945/1946 (Volume 27)
    - 1946/1947 (Volume 28)
    - Summer Session Budgets, 1933-1946 (Volume 29)
  - Miscellaneous Unit Budgets
    - University Hospital
      - 1928/1929-1931/1932 (Box 204)
      - 1951/1952 (Volume 32)
      - 1952/1953 (Volume 33)
      - 1953/1954 (Volume 34)
      - 1954/1955 (Volume 35)
      - 1955/1956 (Volume 36)
      - 1956/1957 (Volume 37)
      - 1957/1958 (Volume 38)
      - 1958/1959 (Volume 39)
      - 1959/1960 (Volume 40)
      - 1960/1961 (Volume 41)
      - 1961/1962 (Volume 42)
      - 1962/1963 (Volume 43)
      - 1963/1964 (Volume 44)
      - 1964/1965 (Volume 45)
      - 1965/1966 (Volume 46)
      - 1966/1967 (Volume 47)
      - 1968/1968 (Volume 48)
      - 1968/1969 (Volume 49)
      - 1969/1970 (Volume 50)
      - 1970/1971 (Volume 51)
  - Project (Trust Fund) Budget (Annual)
    - 1948/1949 (Volume 30)
    - 1949/1950 (Volume 31)
    - 1950/1951-1952/1953 (Box 34)
    - 1953/1954-1957/1958 (Box 35)
    - 1958/1959-1960/1961 (Box 36)
    - Volume 1-2, 1961/62 (Box 37)
    - Volume 1, 1962/63 (Box 37)
    - Volume 2, 1962/63 (Box 37)
    - Volume 3, 1962/63 (Box 38)
    - Volume 1-3., 1963/64 (Box 38)
    - Volume 1, 1964/65 (Box 38)
    - Volume 2, 1964/65 (Box 39)
    - Volume 3, 1964/65 (Box 39)
    - Volume 4, 1964/65 (Box 39)
    - Volume 5, 1964/65 (Box 39)
    - Volume 1, 1965/66 (Box 39)
    - Volume 2, 1965/66 (Box 39)
    - Volume 3, 1965/66 (Box 40)
    - Volume 4, 1965/66 (Box 40)
    - Volume 5, 1965/66 (Box 40)
    - Volume 1, 1966/67 (Box 40)
    - Volume 2, 1966/67 (Box 40)
    - Volume 3, 1966/67 (Box 40)
    - Volume 4, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 5, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 6, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 7, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 8, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 9, 1966/67 (Box 41)
    - Volume 1, 1967/68 (Box 41)
    - Volume 2, 1967/68 (Box 41)
    - Volume 3, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 4, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 5, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 6, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 7, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 8, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 9, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 10, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 11, 1967/68 (Box 42)
    - Volume 12, 1967/68 (Box 43)
    - Volume 1, 1968/69 (Box 43)
    - Volume 2, 1968/69 (Box 43)
    - Volume 3, 1968/69 (Box 43)
    - Volume 4, 1968/69 (Box 43)
    - Volume 5, 1968/69 (Box 43)
    - Volume 6, 1968/69 (Box 44)
    - Volume 1, 1969/70 (Box 44)
    - Volume 2, 1969/70 (Box 44)
    - Volume 3, 1969/70 (Box 44)
    - Volume 4, 1969/70 (Box 44)
    - Volume 5, 1969/70 (Box 45)
    - Volume 6, 1969/70 (Box 45)
    - Volume 1, 1970/71 (Box 45)
    - Volume 2, 1970/71 (Box 45)
    - Volume 3, 1970/71 (Box 45)
    - Volume 4, 1970/71 (Box 45)
    - Volume 5, 1970/71 (Box 46)
    - Volume 1-5, 1971/72 (Box 46)
    - Volume 1-/6, 1972/73 (Box 47)
    - Volume 1, 1973/74 (Box 47)
    - Volume 2, 1973/74 (Box 47)
    - Volume 3, 1973/74 (Box 48)
    - Volume 4, 1973/74 (Box 48)
    - Volume 5, 1973/74 (Box 48)
    - Volume 6, 1973/74 (Box 48)
    - Volume 7, 1973/74 (Box 48)
    - Volume 1, 1974/75 (Box 48)
    - Volume 2, 1974/75 (Box 48)
    - Volume 3, 1974/75 (Box 48)
    - Volume 4, 1974/75 (Box 48)
    - Volume 5, 1974/75 (Box 49)
    - Volume 6, 1974/75 (Box 49)
    - Volume 1-5, 1975/76 (Box 49)
    - Volume 1, 1976/77 (Box 49)
    - Volume 2, 1976/77 (Box 50)
    - Volume 3, 1976/77 (Box 50)
    - Volume 4, 1976/77 (Box 50)
    - Volume 5, 1976/77 (Box 50)
    - Volume. 1-7, 1977/78 (Box 50)
- Assistant to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer
  - Topical Files, 1940-1988
    The Assistant to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer topical files, measuring 8 linear feet and covering the period 1940-1988 (bulk 1960-1980) (1996 accession, boxes 77-84), was compiled by William Sturgis, who filled this position from 1974 to 1991. These files augment the main topical files received in previous accessions, but include documentation unique to the assistant position. The assistant position, held by John McKevitt, and after a gap of several years, by Sturgis, included involvement in plant extension planning, programming building space and acting as legislative liaison for building appropriations.
    These records cover Sturgis' tenure and include some materials from McKevitt's period (1955-1969). Sturgis kept thorough records of the many committees he sat on, particularly the plant extension committee and the faculty advisory committee to the vice president. The latter committee was formally known as the SACUA Committee on Campus Planning and Development until 1971, when the name was changed to SACUA Advisory Committee on Financial Affairs. Sturgis was secretary for this committee.
    Sturgis was involved with a wide range of urban planning issues affecting both Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan and was a member of the joint university-city relations committee. He was also involved with various committees concerning specific issues, including the development of North Campus, student parking, fire and security forces, housing and funding for recreational facilities. The file names created by Sturgis have been used except in a few cases where more information has been supplied, and the files are arranged in alphabetical order.
    - 1940-1988
      - Ann Arbor Historic Districts, 1979-1980 (Box 77)
      - Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti Urban Area Transportation Study Committee, 1977 (Box 77)
      - Annual Reports, 1959-1969 (Box 77)
      - Arborcrest Cemetery, 1950-1978 (Box 77)
      - Arboretum, 1957-1964 (Box 77)
      - Architectural Services, 1949-1979 (Box 77)
      - Astronomy-McMath-Hulbert Observatory, 1974-1979 (Box 77)
      - Astronomy-Telescope Relocation to Arizona, 1974-1983 (Box 77)
      - Astronomy Building (including telescope, dome and shop), 1961-1976; 4 folders (Box 77)
      - Athletics
        - Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramural and Club Sports (ACRIS), User Fee Subcommittee, 1973-1976; 2 folders (Box 77)
        - Committee to Seek Additional Funding for Recreational Facilities, 1973; 2 folders (Box 77)
        - Intercollegiate Athletics-Revenue/Expense, 1972-1982 (Box 77)
        - Recreational and Intramural Sports, 1968-1980; 4 folders (Box 77)
        - Title IX, 1976-1980 (Box 77)
        - Women's Intercollegiate Athletics, 1973-1976 (Box 77)
      - Barbour-Waterman Gymnasiums-Regents' Report, November, 1976 (Box 77)
      - Barbour-Waterman Gymnasiums-Relocation, 1976-1977 (Box 77)
      - Biological Station-Douglas Lake, 1971-1984; 4 folders (Box 77)
      - Biological Station-National Natural Landmark, 1979-1980 (Box 77)
      - Black Action Movement, March, 1970 (Box 77)
      - Boathouse Site, Huron River, 1979-1980 (Box 77)
      - Building Inventories (by program), 1940-1966 (Box 78)
      - Building Lists, Chronological up to, 1959 (Box 78)
      - Building Names, 1968-1987 (Box 78)
      - Building Summary Sheets, 1963-1966 (Box 78)
      - Buildings-Leased Space, 1968-1977 (Box 78)
      - Buildings-Leased Space, Kneer Report (Box 78)
      - Buildings-Square Feet and Cost Analysis, 1951-1969; 5 folders (Box 78)
      - Bureau of Commercial Fisheries, 1962-1967 (Box 78)
      - Business Office-Slides and Pictures (Box 78)
      - Business Operations-Misc. Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 78)
      - Business Operations-Student Interns, 1965-1972 (Box 78)
      - Campus Communications Cable System, Feasibility Study, 1973 (Box 78)
      - Campus Disturbance, 28, April 1972 (Box 78)
      - Campus Disturbance, 19, May 1972 (Box 78)
      - Campus Identification Signs, 1963-1974 (Box 78)
      - Campus Plan Advisory Committee, 1961-1964 (Box 78)
      - Campus Planning (Staff), 1961-1966; 7 folders (Box 78)
      - Campus Walkways and Lighting, 1963-1974 (Box 78)